<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../transforms/pp2html.xsl"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/commoncriteria/transforms/master/schemas/CCPackage.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>


<Package name="X.509"
  xmlns="https://niap-ccevs.org/cc/v1"
  xmlns:sec="https://niap-ccevs.org/cc/v1/section"
  xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <project-notes>
   
 </project-notes>

  <PPReference>
   <ReferenceTable>
      <PPTitle>Functional Package for X.509</PPTitle>
      <PPVersion>1.0</PPVersion>
      <PPAuthor>National Information Assurance Partnership</PPAuthor>
      <PPPubDate>2023-12-14</PPPubDate>
      <Keywords>X.509; certificates; PKI</Keywords>
    </ReferenceTable>
  </PPReference>
  
  <RevisionHistory>
  	<entry>
      <version>1.0</version>
      <date>2023-12-14</date>
      <subject>Initial draft.</subject>
  	</entry>
  </RevisionHistory>
	
<!-- PP-style preferences   -->
  <pp-preferences>
<!--        <pp-pref name="display-audit-with-sfrs">0</pp-pref> -->
    <audit-events-in-sfrs/>
  </pp-preferences>

	
<!-- 			-->
<!-- 1.0 Introduction   -->
<!-- 			-->
<sec:Introduction>
	
<!-- 			-->
<!-- 1.1 Overview	-->
<!--			-->
  <sec:Overview>
        <h:p>
        	X.509 is an International Telecommunication Union Telecommunication Standardization Sector (ITU-T) standard for public key certificates.
        	Public key certificates are used as authentication mechanisms for trusted communications protocols and as integrity verification methods.
      	</h:p><h:p>
		This <h:i>Functional Package (FP) for X.509</h:i> provides a collection of X.509 
      		Security Functional Requirements (SFRs) and 
		Evaluation Activities (EAs) for the issuance, use, and validation of X.509 certificates. The intent 
		of this FP is to provide Protection Profile (PP), collaborative Protection Profile (cPP), and Protection Profile Module (PP-Module) authors 
		with a readily consumable collection of SFRs and EAs to be integrated into
		their documents.  
        </h:p>
   </sec:Overview>

<!-- 			-->
<!-- 1.2 Terms		-->
<!-- 1.2.1 Common Criteria Terms -->
<!-- 1.2.2 Technology Terms -->
<!--			-->
   <tech-terms>
   	<suppress>Extended Package, TSF Interface</suppress>
   	<term full="Connection">The SSH transport layer between a client and a server.  Within a connection there can
			be multiple sessions. </term>
   	<term abbr="CA" full="Certification Authority"></term>
   	<term abbr="cPP" full="collaborative Protection Profile"></term>
   	<term abbr="CMC" full="Certificate Management over CMS"></term>
   	<term abbr="CMS" full="Cryptographic Message Syntax"></term>
   	<term abbr="CRL" full="Certificate Revocation List"></term>
   	<term abbr="CSR" full="Certificate Signing Request"></term>
   	<term abbr="EA" full="Evaluation Activity"></term>
   	<term abbr="EC" full="Elliptic Curve"></term>
   	<term abbr="EKU" full="extendedKeyUsage"></term>
   	<term abbr="EST" full="Enrollment over Secure Transport"></term>
   	<term abbr="FP" full="Functional Package"></term>
   	<term abbr="HTTP" full="Hypertext Transfer Protocol"></term>
   	<term abbr="HTTPS" full="Hypertext Transfer Protocol Secure"></term>
   	<term abbr="ITU-T" full="International Telecommunication Union Telecommunication Standardization Sector"></term>
   	<term abbr="OCSP" full="Online Certificate Status Protocol"></term>
   	<term abbr="OE" full="Operational Environment"></term>
   	<term abbr="OID" full="Object Identifiers"></term>
   	<term abbr="OS" full="Operating System"></term>
   	<term abbr="PP" full="Protection Profile"></term>
   	<term abbr="PP-Module" full="Protection Profile Module"></term>
   	<term abbr="RA" full="Registration Authority"></term>
   	<term abbr="RBG" full="Random Bit Generator"></term>
   	<term abbr="RFC" full="Request for Comment"></term>
   	<term abbr="SFR" full="Security Functional Requirement"></term>
   	<term abbr="ST" full="Security Target"></term>
   	<term abbr="TLS" full="Transport Layer Security"></term>
   	<term abbr="TOE" full="Target of Evaluation"></term>
   	<term abbr="TSF" full="TOE Security Functionality"></term>
   	<term abbr="TSS" full="TOE Summary Specification"></term>
   </tech-terms>
	
     
<!-- 			-->
<!-- 1.3 Compliant Targets of Evaluation	-->
<!--			-->
    <sec:toes title="Compliant Targets of Evaluation">
    	    	
		<h:p>The Target of Evaluation (TOE) in this FP is the portion of a product that provides X.509 capabilities to other portions of the TOE Security Functionality (TSF), such as 
			functions for subject authentication, 
			trusted communications, validation of TOE software and firmware updates, or integrity verification as part of self-testing. 
			At minimum, a conformant TOE will include the ability to validate X.509 certificates presented to it, including:
			<h:ul>
				<h:li>cryptographic validity of the digital signature.</h:li>
				<h:li>time-based validity.</h:li>
				<h:li>issuer-based validity.</h:li>
				<h:li>revocation status using a Certificate Revocation List (CRL) or the Online Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP).</h:li>
				<h:li>validation that the certificate's extensions are consistent with its intended use.</h:li>
			</h:ul>A conformant TOE must also define its intended uses for X.509 certificates and how to proceed when a certificate with undetermined 
			revocation status is presented to it.
			</h:p><h:p>
			This FP also defines mechanisms by which the TSF can generate a Certificate Signing Request (CSR) for receiving a signed certificate from a 
			Certification Authority (CA). This may be generated either as a file that is provided to a CA manually or done via an active network connection to the 
			CA using Enrollment over Secure Transport (EST).
			</h:p><h:p>
			There may also be some situations where revocation checking is not performed. This FP defines an optional requirement for cases where exceptions
			to the claimed revocation functionality exist.
			</h:p><h:p>
			Lastly, the X.509 functionality defined by this FP is part of a TOE, but is not considered to be an entire TOE on its own. X.509 functionality
			is implemented by a wide variety of technology products, some of which are standalone and some dependent on a trusted platform
			(such as a software application on a general-purpose computer or mobile device). Auditable events have been defined for the SFRs in this FP for cases
			where the TOE boundary includes an audit function specified by FAU_GEN.1. A TOE that conforms to this FP may also implement or rely on its operational
			environment to implement appropriate management functionality for X.509 functionality that may include:
			<h:ul>
				<h:li>specifying root and intermediate CA certificates to be used as trust anchors.</h:li>
				<h:li>generating certificate requests and loading signed certificates for the TOE's own use into its trust store.</h:li>
				<h:li>specifying the revocation method that is used.</h:li>
				<h:li>configuring how the TOE behaves in the event that certificate revocation information is unavailable.</h:li>
			</h:ul>
			Any conformant TOE must consider the extent to which X.509 functionality must be managed, and ensure that appropriate management claims are made in 
			the TOE's Security Target (ST) or that the TOE conforms to a PP that allows a trusted platform in its Operational Environment (OE) to implement them.
			</h:p><h:p>
			This FP describes the extended security functionality of X.509 in terms of <xref g="CC"/>. </h:p>
		<h:p>The contents of this FP must be appropriately incorporated into a PP, cPP, or PP-Module. When this FP 
		is incorporated as such, the ST must include selection-based requirements in accordance with the selections or assignments 
		indicated in the incorporating document.
		</h:p><h:p>The PP, cPP, or PP-Module that instantiates this FP must typically include the following components in order to satisfy 
		dependencies of this FP. It is the responsibility of the PP, cPP, or PP-Module author who incorporates this FP to 
		ensure that dependence on these components is satisfied, either by the TOE or by assumptions about its OE.
		</h:p><h:p>An ST must identify in its conformance claims, the applicable version of the PP, cPP, or PP-Module, and of this
		FP.</h:p>
		<componentsneeded>
			<componentneeded>
				<componentid>FCS_CKM.1</componentid>
				<notes>To support public and private key pair generation for creating an X.509 CSR, the PP or PP-Module must
					include FCS_CKM.1 and specify the corresponding algorithms.</notes>
			</componentneeded>
			<componentneeded>
				<componentid>FCS_COP.1</componentid>
				<notes>
					To support the cryptography needed for X.509 validation, the PP or PP-Module must include FCS_COP.1 
					(iterating as needed) to specify appropriate digital signature validation and hash algorithms for the
					X.509 certificates presented to the TOE.
				</notes>
			</componentneeded>
			<!-- The components in the PP or PP-Module that need this SFR should require it;
			it is not _directly_ depended upon by this Package.-->
			<componentneeded>
				<componentid>FCS_RBG.1</componentid>
				<notes>To support the Random Bit Generation (RBG) needed for public and private key pair generation,
					the PP or PP-Module must include FCS_RBG.1 or an extended SFR that defines comparable functionality.</notes>
			</componentneeded>
			<componentneeded>
			<componentid>FPT_STM.1</componentid>
				<notes>To support validating whether a presented X.509 certificate is expired, 
					the PP or PP-Module must include FPT_STM.1 or some other requirement that ensures reliable system time.  
					</notes>
			</componentneeded>
			<componentneeded>
				<componentid>FTP_PRO.1</componentid>
				<notes>To support EST when claimed, the PP or PP-Module must include 
					FTP_PRO.1 or equivalent extended SFRs to define the Hypertext Transfer Protocol Secure (HTTPS) and Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol implementation for these communications.
					Note that support for EST is not mandatory.
				</notes>
			</componentneeded>
			<componentneeded>
				<componentid>FTP_PRO.2</componentid>
				<notes>To support EST when claimed, the PP or PP-Module must include 
					FTP_PRO.2 or equivalent extended SFRs to define the HTTPS and TLS protocol implementation for these communications.
					Note that support for EST is not mandatory.
				</notes>
			</componentneeded>
			<componentneeded>
				<componentid>FTP_PRO.3</componentid>
				<notes>To support EST when claimed, the PP or PP-Module must include 
					FTP_PRO.3 or equivalent extended SFRs to define the HTTPS and TLS protocol implementation for these communications.
					Note that support for EST is not mandatory.
				</notes>
			</componentneeded>
			<componentneeded>
				<componentid>FTP_ITC.1</componentid>
				<notes>To support EST when claimed, the PP or PP-Module must include FTP_ITC.1 to define a trusted channel
					between the TOE and a trusted CA.
					Note that support for EST is not mandatory.
				</notes>
			</componentneeded>
			
		</componentsneeded>
	</sec:toes>
</sec:Introduction>
  
<!-- 			-->
<!-- 2.0 Conformance Claims	-->
<!--			-->
<sec:Conformance_Claims boilerplate="no">
	<cclaims>
		<cclaim name="Conformance Statement">
			<description>An ST must claim exact conformance to this FP.
				<h:br/><h:br/>
				The evaluation methods used for evaluating the TOE are a combination of the workunits defined in <xref to="bibCEM"/>, as well as the
				EAs for ensuring that individual SFRs have a sufficient level of supporting evidence in the ST and 
				guidance documentation, and have been sufficiently tested by the laboratory as part of completing ATE_IND.1.
			</description>
		</cclaim>
		<cclaim name="CC Conformance Claims">
			<description>This FP is conformant to Part 2 (extended) of Common Criteria CC:2022, Revision 1. FPs
			do not contain any SARs, so no CC Part 3 claim is made.</description>
		</cclaim>
		<cclaim name="PP Claim">
			<description>This FP does not claim conformance to any PP.<h:br/><h:br/>
				PP-Configurations do not require enumeration of FPs; this FP can be claimed in any PP-Configuration that includes
				a PP or PP-Module that permits the FP to be claimed as part of it.
			</description>
		</cclaim>
		<cclaim name="Package Claim">
			<description>This FP does not claim conformance to any other FPs.
			</description>
		</cclaim>
	</cclaims>
</sec:Conformance_Claims>

<!-- 				-->
<!-- 3.0 Security Requirements 	-->
<!--				-->
	
<!-- 			-->
<!-- 3.1 Security Functional Requirements 	-->
<!--			-->
<sec:Security_Functional_Requirements>

	<!-- Audit table for mandatory requirements  -->
	<sec:ss-audit-table title="Auditable Events for Mandatory SFRs">
		<h:p>
			The auditable events specified in this FP are included in an ST 
			if the incorporating PP, cPP, or PP-Module supports audit event reporting through FAU_GEN.1,
			and if all other criteria in the incorporating PP or PP-Module are met.
		</h:p>
		<audit-table id="at-man-audit" table="mandatory">
			<h:div class="table-caption"><ctr ctr-type="Table" id="atref-mandatory">: Auditable Events for Mandatory SFRs</ctr></h:div>
		</audit-table>
	</sec:ss-audit-table>
	  
	<!-- 			-->
	<!-- 3.1.1 FIA: Identification and Authentication -->
	<!--			-->
	<sec:fia title="Identification and Authentication (FIA)">

		<ext-comp-def fam-id="FIA_X509_EXT" title="X.509 Certificate Handling">
			<fam-behavior>This family defines the behavior and use of X.509 certificates for functions to
				be performed by the TSF. Components in this family require validation of certificates
				according to a specified set of rules, use of certificates for authentication for protocols and
				integrity verification, generation of certificate requests, certificate enrollment, and revocation checking behavior.
				
			</fam-behavior>
		</ext-comp-def>
		
		<f-component name="X.509 Certificate Validation" cc-id="fia_x509_ext.1">
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-1e1">
				<title>
					The <selectables>
						<selectable>TSF</selectable>
						<selectable>TOE platform</selectable></selectables> <comment>TOE vs platform selection added globally, of course if the TOE doesn't have a 'platform' (e.g. NDcPP) the
							PP author can just force the selection of "TSF".</comment>
					shall validate certificates in accordance with the following rules:
					<h:ul> 
						<h:li>RFC 5280 certificate validation and certificate path validation supporting a minimum path length of 
							<assignable>positive integer</assignable> 
							shall be used.</h:li>
						<h:li>The certification path shall terminate with a trusted CA certificate designated as a trust anchor.</h:li>
						<h:li>All CA certificates in the certification path shall contain the basicConstraints extension with 
							the CA flag set to TRUE.</h:li> <comment>This covers basically the same thing as FIA_X509_EXT.1.2 (The TSF shall only treat a certificate as a CA
								certificate if the basicConstraints extension is present and the CA flag is set to TRUE) so there appears to
								be no need to have a second element.</comment>
						<h:li>The revocation status of the certificate shall be validated using <selectables linebreak="yes">
							<selectable>The OCSP as specified in RFC 6960</selectable>
							<selectable>CRLs as specified in RFC 5280 and refined by RFC 8603</selectable>
							<selectable>An OCSP TLS Status Request Extension (OCSP stapling) as specified in RFC 6066</selectable>
							<selectable>An OCSP TLS Multiple Certificate Status Request Extension (OCSP multi-stapling) as specified
								in RFC 6961</selectable>
						</selectables> <comment>Added to accommodate exception checking for revocation (see TD0605).</comment>and with <selectables>
							<selectable>no exceptions</selectable>
							<selectable id="revocation-exceptions-exist">exceptions defined in <xref to="fia-x509-ext-5"/></selectable></selectables></h:li>
						<h:li>The TSF shall validate the extendedKeyUsage (EKU) field according to the following rules: 
							<selectables linebreak="yes">
							<selectable>Certificates used for trusted updates and executable code integrity verification shall have the
								Code Signing Purpose (id-kp 3 with OID 1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.3).</selectable>
							<selectable>Client certificates presented for TLS shall have the Client Authentication purpose
								(id-kp 2 with OID 1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.2).</selectable>
							<selectable>Server certificates presented for TLS shall have the Server Authentication purpose
										(id-kp 1 with OID 1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.1).</selectable>
							<selectable>Delegated OCSP signer’s certificates presented for OCSP responses shall have the OCSP
										Signing purpose (id-kp 9 with OID 1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.9).</selectable>
							<selectable>Server certificates presented for EST shall have the Certificate Management over CMS (CMC) Registration Authority (RA)
										purpose (id-kp-cmcRA with OID 1.3.6.1.5.5.7.3.28).</selectable>
								<selectable><assignable>other expected EKU values</assignable></selectable></selectables></h:li> <comment>This would cover
									S/MIME extensions as well as a catch-all/future proofing for anything else not currently listed.</comment>
							<comment>General note about the open-ended assignments - they are here so that PPs that use this FP can
								accommodate things that we haven't anticipated through refinements/completing the assignment. If a PP
								adds stuff here, the PP can also update the EA with specific details needed for that permutation. So I
								don't think that having an open-ended assignment here with no corresponding EA violates the spirit of
								exact conformance. We just need to make it clear to PP authors that this is how it's intended to be used
								(they can always fill out the assignment with 'no other' themselves and then there is no gap in the EAs).</comment>
							<h:li><selectables>
							<selectable>no other rules</selectable>
								<selectable><assignable>additional certificate evaluation rules</assignable></selectable></selectables>
								<comment>Catch-all added to the end just in case other rules are ever relevant (for example FDP_CER_EXT.1 in the CA PP
									requires a CA to generate certs that use the certificate policy field but we don't have any rules for validating that
									field's contents).</comment>
						</h:li>
								</h:ul>
					</title>
				<aactivity>
					<TSS>
						<h:p>The evaluator shall ensure the TOE Summary Specification (TSS) describes where the check of validity of the certificates takes place
							(both in terms of circumstances as well as whether the TSF or the TOE platform is responsible for certificate
							validation in each case) and that the TSS identifies the rules for certificate field checking. In cases
							where a certificate is used in an authentication step or for validating the integrity of trusted updates,
							it is expected that revocation checking will be performed. If X.509 certificates are used for power-on
							self-tests, it is not necessary to verify certificate revocation status.
						</h:p>
						
						<h:p>The TSS shall describe when revocation checking is performed and on what certificates. If the revocation
							checking during authentication is handled differently depending on whether a full certificate chain or only
							a leaf certificate is being presented, any differences must be summarized in the TSS and explained in the
							operational guidance.
						</h:p>
					</TSS>
					<Guidance>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall ensure that the operational guidance describes where the check of validity of the
							certificates takes place and any of the rules for EKU fields.
						</h:p>
						
						<h:p>
							If the revocation checking method is configurable, the evaluator shall ensure that the operational guidance describes
							how to specify the revocation checking method used, as well as any other implementation details for configuration of
							the revocation check function.
						</h:p>
					</Guidance>
					<Tests>
						<comment>Synthesized from NDcPP (modified by TD0527) and App PP (modified by TD0669) - may need some additional
							modification/tailoring for broader usage.</comment>
						<h:p>
							The tests described must be performed in conjunction with the other certificate services evaluation
							activities, <comment>Do we want to do it this way or should everything be self-contained to the SFR it's
								referenced in?</comment>including the functions in <xref to="fia-x509-ext-2e1"/>. The tests for the EKU rules are
							performed together with the uses that require those rules. If the TSF supports chains of length four
							or greater, the evaluator shall create a chain of at least four certificates: the node certificate to be
							tested, two intermediate CAs, and the Root CA. If the TSF supports chains of length three, then only one
							intermediate CA shall be created. If the TSF supports a maximum chain of length two, then a chain with no
							intermediate CAs shall be created.
						</h:p>
						<testlist>
							<test> 
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall demonstrate that validating a certificate without a valid certification path results
							in the function failing, for each of the following reasons, in turn:
						</h:p>
							<h:ul>
								<h:li>
									Establishing a certificate path in which one of the issuing certificates is not a CA certificate
								</h:li>
								<h:li>
									Omitting the basicConstraints field in one of the issuing certificates
								</h:li>
								<h:li>
									Setting the basicConstraints field in an issuing certificate to have CA=False
								</h:li>
								<h:li>
									Omitting the CA signing bit of the key usage field in an issuing certificate
								</h:li>
								<h:li>
									Setting the path length field of a valid CA field to a value strictly less than the certificate path
								</h:li>
							</h:ul>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall then establish a valid certificate path consisting of valid CA certificates, and
							demonstrate that the function succeeds. The evaluator shall then remove trust in one of the CA
							certificates, and show that the function fails.
						</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall demonstrate that validating an expired certificate results in the function failing.
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>The evaluator shall test that the TOE can properly handle revoked certificates, conditional on
								whether CRL, OCSP, OCSP stapling, or OCSP multi-stapling is selected; if multiple methods are selected,
								then the following tests shall be performed for each method:
								<h:ul>
									<h:li>
										The evaluator shall test revocation of the node certificate.
									</h:li>
									<h:li>
										If intermediate CA certificates are supported, the evaluator shall also test revocation of an intermediate CA certificate (i.e., the intermediate
										CA certificate should be revoked by the Root CA).
										If OCSP stapling per RFC 6066 is the only supported revocation method, this test is omitted.
									</h:li>
									<h:li>
										The evaluator shall ensure that a valid certificate is used and that the validation function succeeds. The
										evaluator shall then attempt the test with a certificate that has been revoked (for each method chosen in the selection)
										to ensure when the certificate is no longer valid that the validation function fails.
									</h:li>
								</h:ul>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									If any OCSP option is selected, the evaluator shall ensure the TSF has no other source of revocation
									information available and configure the OCSP server, or use a man-in-the-middle tool to present an
									OCSP response signed by a certificate that does not have the OCSP signing purpose and which is the
									only source of revocation status information advertised by the CA issuing the certificate being
									validated. The evaluator shall verify that validation of the OCSP response fails and that the TOE
									treats the certificate being checked as invalid and rejects the connection. If CRL is selected, the
									evaluator shall also configure the CA to be the only source of revocation status information
									and sign a CRL with a certificate that does not have the cRLSign key usage bit. The evaluator shall
									verify that validation of the CRL fails and that the TOE treats the certificate being checked as
									invalid and rejects the connection.
								</h:p>
								
								<h:p>
									Note: The intent of this test is to ensure a TOE does not trust invalid revocation status information.
									A TOE receiving invalid revocation status information from the only advertised certificate status
									provider should treat the certificate whose status is being checked as invalid. This should generally
									be treated differently from the case where the TSF is not able to establish a connection to check
									revocation status information, but it is acceptable that the TSF ignore any invalid information and
									attempt to find another source of revocation status (another advertised provider, a locally configured
									provider, or cached information) and treat this situation as not having a connection to a valid
									certificate status provider.
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall modify any byte in the first eight bytes of the certificate and demonstrate that
									the certificate fails to validate (i.e., the certificate will fail to parse correctly).
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall modify any byte in the last byte of the certificate and demonstrate that the
									certificate fails to validate (i.e., the signature on the certificate will not validate).	
								</h:p>
							</test>							
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall modify any byte in the public key of the certificate and demonstrate that the
									certificate fails to validate (i.e., the signature on the certificate will not validate).
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test id="fia-x509-ext-1e8">
								<h:p>
									[Conditional on support for Elliptic Curve (EC)] The evaluator shall establish a valid, trusted
									certificate chain consisting of an EC leaf certificate, an EC intermediate CA certificate not
									designated as a trust anchor, and an EC certificate designated as a trust anchor, where the
									EC parameters are specified as a named curve. The evaluator shall confirm that the TOE
									validates the certificate chain.	
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									(Conditional on support for EC certificates) The evaluator shall replace the intermediate
									certificate in the certificate chain for the previous test with a modified certificate, where the
									modified intermediate CA has a public key information field where the EC parameters use an explicit
									format version of the EC parameters in the public key information field of the
									intermediate CA certificate from <xref to="fia-x509-ext-1e8"/>, and the modified intermediate CA certificate is signed by
									the trusted EC Root CA,  but having no other changes. The evaluator shall confirm the TOE treats the
									certificate as invalid.
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									(Conditional on support for EC certificates) The evaluator shall establish a subordinate CA
									certificate where the EC parameters are specified as a named curve that is signed by a
									trusted EC Root CA. The evaluator shall attempt to load the certificate into the trust store and
									observe that it is accepted into the TOE's trust store. The evaluator shall then establish a
									subordinate CA certificate that uses an explicit format version of the EC parameters
									and that is signed by a trusted EC Root CA. The evaluator shall attempt to load the certificate into
									the trust store and observe that it is rejected and not added to the TOE's trust store.
								</h:p>
							</test>
						</testlist>
					</Tests>
				</aactivity>
				
			</f-element>
			
			
			<audit-event>
				<audit-event-descr>Unsuccessful attempt to validate a certificate.</audit-event-descr>
				<audit-event-info>Reason for failure.</audit-event-info>
			</audit-event>
		</f-component>
				
		<f-component name="X.509 Certificate Usage" cc-id="fia_x509_ext.2">
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-2e1">
				<title><comment>Changed from "Authentication" to "Usage" since X.509 can also be used mainly in the
					context of integrity.</comment>
					The
					<selectables>
						<selectable>TSF</selectable>
						<selectable>TOE platform</selectable></selectables>
					shall use X.509v3 certificates as defined by RFC 5280 to support authentication for 
					<selectables>
						<selectable><assignable>trusted communications protocol</assignable></selectable>
						<selectable>no protocols</selectable></selectables>
					and <comment>Added selections based on other uses of X.509 in various PPs - making a distinction between
						"administrators" (of the TSF) vs "users" (in the context of an organizational user the TSF is authenticating
						but who may not use the TOE directly, e.g. when the TOE functions as an authentication server).</comment>
					<selectables>
						<selectable>code signing for system software updates</selectable>
						<selectable>code signing for software integrity testing</selectable>
						<selectable>integrity verification for TSF protected data</selectable>
						<selectable>Administrator authentication</selectable>
						<selectable>User authentication</selectable>
						<selectable><assignable>other uses</assignable></selectable>
						<selectable>no additional uses</selectable></selectables>.
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-2e2">
				<title>When the
					<selectables>
						<selectable>TSF</selectable>
						<selectable>TOE platform</selectable></selectables>
					cannot establish a connection to determine the validity of a certificate, the TSF shall
					<selectables>
						<selectable>allow the Administrator to choose whether to accept the certificate in these cases</selectable>
						<selectable>accept the certificate</selectable>
						<selectable>not accept the certificate</selectable></selectables>.
				</title>
			<aactivity> 
					<TSS>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall check the TSS to ensure that it describes how the TOE chooses which certificates to use.
						</h:p><comment>Guidance activities were removed from this.</comment>
						
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall examine the TSS to confirm that it describes the behavior of the TOE when a connection
							cannot be established during the certificate's validity check.<comment>This used to say "used in
								establishing a trusted channel" but it seems like there is no reason that it should be limited to that
								since the same behavior will need to be described in non-trusted channel cases.</comment>. The evaluator shall verify that any
							distinctions between trusted channels are described.
						</h:p>
					</TSS>
				<Guidance><comment>The first part of the paragraph from ND-SD is not very clear on its intent so I've removed it. The
					text from TSS that referred to guidance has been moved down to here. 		
					("The evaluator shall ensure that the guidance documentation describes the configuration required in the operating
					environment so the TOE can use the certificates. The guidance documentation shall also include any required
					configuration on the TOE to use the certificates").</comment>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall verify that the operational guidance determines the TOE chooses which certificates to use
							for authentication.
						</h:p>
						
						<h:p>
							If the TSS claims that the Administrator can specify the default action in the case of an undetermined
							revocation status, the evaluator shall ensure that the guidance documentation contains instructions on how
							this configuration action is performed.
						</h:p>
					</Guidance>
					<Tests>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall perform the following tests for each trusted channel: <comment>Trusted channel testing is
								synthesized from NDcPP/App PP. User/admin authentication is taken from GPOS PP.								
								Note that we also still need something for the other uses for X.509 authentication (e.g. code signing for
								updates or integrity) - these were not explicitly covered through X.509 requirements in other PPs
								(e.g. if code signing for updates is used, then it would be tested under FPT_TUD_EXT). They should probably
								be all merged under X.509 so they aren't forked in different PPs.</comment>
						</h:p>
						<testlist>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall demonstrate that a valid certificate that requires certificate validation
									checking to be performed in at least some part by communicating with a non-TOE IT entity is accepted. The
									evaluator shall then manipulate the environment so that the TOE is unable to verify the validity of
									the certificate and observe that the action selected in <xref to="fia-x509-ext-2e2"/> is performed. If the selected
									action is Administrator-configurable, then the evaluator shall follow the guidance documentation to
									determine that all supported Administrator-configurable options behave in their documented manner.
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall demonstrate that an invalid certificate that requires certificate validation
									checking to be performed in at least some part by communicating with a non-TOE IT entity cannot be
									accepted.
								</h:p>
								
								<h:p>
									If the TSF uses X.509 certificates for Administrator or User authentication, the evaluator shall
									generate an X.509v3 certificate for a User with the Client Authentication EKU field set. The
									evaluator will provision the Operating System (OS) for authentication with the X.509v3 certificate.
								</h:p>
								
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall ensure that the certificates are validated by the OS per <xref to="fia-x509-ext-1e1"/>, and then
									conduct the following two tests.
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall attempt to authenticate to the TOE using a valid X.509v3 certificate. The
									evaluator shall ensure that the authentication attempt is successful.
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall generate a second certificate that is identical to the first except for the public
									key and any values derived from the public key. The evaluator shall attempt to authenticate to the
									TOE with this certificate. The evaluator shall ensure that the authentication attempt is unsuccessful.
								</h:p>
							</test>
						</testlist>
					</Tests>
			</aactivity>
			</f-element>
			<audit-event/>
		</f-component>
		
		<f-component name="X.509 Certificate Requests" cc-id="fia_x509_ext.3" status="optional">
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-3e1">
				<title>The
					<selectables>
						<selectable>TSF</selectable>
						<selectable>TOE platform</selectable></selectables>
					shall generate a certificate request as specified by RFC 2986, and be able to provide the following information in the
					request: public key and 
					<selectables>
						<selectable>device-specific information</selectable>
						<selectable>Common Name</selectable>
						<selectable>Organization</selectable>
						<selectable>Organizational Unit</selectable>
						<selectable>Country</selectable>
						<selectable><assignable>other information</assignable><comment>Assignment added as a catch-all/future proofing
							for anything we may have missed - if this is redundant because "device-specific information" covers it then
							remove and update the EA accordingly.</comment></selectable></selectables>.
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-3e2">
				<title>The
					<selectables>
						<selectable>TSF</selectable>
						<selectable>TOE platform</selectable></selectables>
					shall validate the chain of certificates from the Root CA upon receiving the CA certificate response.
				</title>
				<aactivity> 
					<TSS>
						<h:p>
							If the ST author selects "device-specific information" or “other information,” the evaluator shall verify
							that the TSS contains a description of the device-specific fields used in certificate requests.
						</h:p>
					</TSS>
					<Guidance>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall check to ensure that the guidance documentation contains instructions on requesting
							certificates from a CA, including generation of a certificate request. If the ST author selects "Common Name",
							"Organization", "Organizational Unit", or "Country", the evaluator shall ensure that this guidance includes
							instructions for establishing these fields before creating the certificate request.
						</h:p>
					</Guidance>
					<Tests>
						<testlist>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall use the guidance documentation to cause the TOE to generate a certificate request.
									The evaluator shall capture the generated message and ensure that it conforms to the format specified.
									The evaluator shall confirm that the certificate request provides the public key and other required
									information, including any necessary User-input information.
								</h:p>
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall demonstrate that validating a response message to a certificate request without a
									valid certification path results in the function failing. The evaluator shall then load one or more
									certificates into the TOE's trust store that are used as CAs to validate the certificate
									response message and demonstrate that the function succeeds.
								</h:p>
							</test>
						</testlist>
					</Tests>
				</aactivity>
			</f-element>
									
			<audit-event/>
		</f-component>
		
		<f-component name="X.509 Certificate Enrollment" cc-id="fia_x509_ext.4" status="optional">
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-4e1">
				<title>The TSF shall use the EST protocol as specified in RFC 7030 to request
					certificate enrollment using the simple enrollment method described in RFC 7030, Section 4.2.
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-4e2">
				<title>The TSF shall be capable of authenticating EST requests using an existing certificate and corresponding private
					key as specified by RFC 7030, Section 3.3.2.
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-4e3">
				<title>The TSF shall be capable of authenticating EST requests using Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) basic authentication with a username and
					password as specified by RFC 7030, Section 3.2.3.
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-4e4">
				<title>The TSF shall perform EST server authentication using an Explicit Trust Anchor following the rules described in
					RFC 7030, section 3.6.1.
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-4e5">
				<title>The TSF shall be capable of requesting server-provided private keys as specified in RFC 7030, Section 4.4.
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-4e6">
				<title>The TSF shall be capable of updating its EST-specific Trust Anchor Database using the "Root CA Key Update" process
					described in RFC 7030, Section 4.1.3.					
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-4e7">
				<title>The TSF shall generate a certificate request message for EST as specified in RFC 2986 and be able to provide the
					following information in the request: public key and
					<selectables>
						<selectable>device-specific information</selectable>
						<selectable>Common Name</selectable>
						<selectable>Organization</selectable>
						<selectable>Organizational Unit</selectable>
						<selectable>Country</selectable>
						<selectable><assignable>other information</assignable><comment>Assignment added as a catch-all/future proofing
							for anything we may have missed.</comment></selectable></selectables>.
				</title>
			</f-element>
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-4e8">
				<title>The TSF shall validate the chain of certificates from the Root CA certificate in the Trust Anchor Database to
					the EST Server CA certificate, upon receiving a CA certificate response.				
				</title>
				<aactivity>
					<TSS>
						<comment>This was taken from the MDF PP as-is, but surely there could be one.</comment>
						<h:p>
							There are no TSS EAs for this component.
						</h:p>
					</TSS>
					<Guidance>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall check to ensure that the operational guidance contains instructions on requesting
							certificates from an EST server, including generating a certificate request message.
						</h:p>
					</Guidance>
					<Tests>
						<testlist>
							<test>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall use the operational guidance to cause the TOE to request certificate enrollment from an
							EST server using the simple enrollment method described in RFC 7030, Section 4.2. When doing this, the
							evaluator shall ensure that the certificate request to the server is authenticated using an existing
							certificate and private key as described by RFC 7030, Section 3.3.2. The evaluator shall confirm that the
							resulting certificate is successfully obtained and installed in the TOE key store.
						</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall use the operational guidance to cause the TOE to request certificate enrollment
									from an EST server using the simple enrollment method described in RFC 7030, Section 4.2. When doing
									this, the evaluator shall ensure that the certificate request to the server is authenticated using a
									username and password as described by RFC 7030, Section 3.2.3. The evaluator shall confirm that the
									resulting certificate is successfully obtained and installed in the TOE key store.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall modify the EST server to return a certificate containing a different public key
									than the key included in the TOE’s certificate request. The evaluator shall use the operational
									guidance to cause the TOE to request certificate enrollment from an EST server. The evaluator shall
									confirm that the TOE does not accept the resulting certificate since the public key in the issued
									certificate does not match the public key in the certificate request.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall configure the EST server or use a man-in-the-middle tool to present a server
									certificate to the TOE that is present in the TOE general Trust Anchor Database, but not its
									EST-specific Trust Anchor Database. The evaluator shall cause the TOE to request certificate
									enrollment from the EST server. The evaluator shall verify that the request is not successful.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall configure the EST server or use a man-in-the-middle tool to present an invalid
									certificate. The evaluator shall cause the TOE to request certificate enrollment from the EST server.
									The evaluator shall verify that the request is not successful. The evaluator shall configure the EST
									server or use a man-in-the-middle tool to present a certificate that does not have the CMC RA purpose
									and verify that requests to the EST server fail. The tester shall repeat the test using a valid
									certificate and a certificate that contains the CMC RA purpose and verify that the certificate
									enrollment requests succeed.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall use a packet sniffing tool between the TOE and an EST server. The evaluator shall
									turn on the sniffing tool and cause the TOE to request certificate enrollment from an EST server.
									The evaluator shall verify that the EST protocol interaction occurs over a TLS
									(TLS) protected connection. The evaluator is not expected to decrypt the connection but rather
									observe that the packets conform to the TLS protocol format.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall use the operational guidance to cause the TOE to request a server-provided
									private key and certificate from an EST server. The evaluator shall confirm that the resulting
									private key and certificate are successfully obtained and installed in the TOE key store. 
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall modify the EST server to, in response to a server-provided private key and
									certificate request, return a private key that does not correspond with the public key in the
									returned certificate. The evaluator shall use the operational guidance to cause the TOE to request a
									server-provided private key and certificate. The evaluator shall confirm that the TOE does not accept
									the resulting private key and certificate since the private key and public key do not correspond.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall configure the EST server to provide a "Root CA Key Update" as described in 
									RFC 7030, Section 4.1.3. The evaluator shall cause the TOE to request CA certificates from the EST
									server and confirm that the EST-specific Trust Anchor Database is updated with the new trust
									anchor.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall configure the EST server to provide a "Root CA Key Update" as described in
									RFC 7030, Section 4.1.3 but shall modify part of the NewWithOld certificate’s generated signature.
									The evaluator shall cause the TOE to request CA certificates from the EST server and confirm
									that the EST-specific Trust Anchor Database is not updated with the new trust anchor since the
									signature did not verify.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
							<test>
								<h:p>
									The evaluator shall use the operational guidance to cause the TOE to generate a certificate request
									message. The evaluator shall capture the generated message and ensure that it conforms to the format
									specified by RFC 2986. The evaluator shall confirm that the certificate request provides the public
									key and other required information, including any necessary User-input information.
								</h:p>	
							</test>
						</testlist>
					</Tests>
				</aactivity>
			</f-element>
			
			
			<audit-event>
				<audit-event-descr>Generation of certificate enrollment request.</audit-event-descr>
				<audit-event-info>Issuer and subject name of EST Server.</audit-event-info>
				<audit-event-info>Method of authentication.</audit-event-info>
				<audit-event-info>Issuer and subject name of certificate used to authenticate.</audit-event-info>
                <audit-event-info>Content of certificate request message.</audit-event-info>
			</audit-event>
			<audit-event>
				<audit-event-descr>Success or failure of enrollment.</audit-event-descr>
				<audit-event-info>Issuer and subject name of added certificate or reason for failure.</audit-event-info>
			</audit-event>
			<audit-event>
				<audit-event-descr>Update of EST trust anchor database.</audit-event-descr>
				<audit-event-info>Subject name of added Root CA.</audit-event-info>
			</audit-event>
		</f-component>
		
		<f-component name="Exceptions to X.509 Certificate Revocation Checking" cc-id="fia_x509_ext.5" id="fia-x509-ext-5" status="sel-based">
			<depends on-sel="revocation-exceptions-exist"/>
			
			<f-element id="fia-x509-ext-5e1">
				<title>The 
					<selectables>
						<selectable>TSF</selectable>
						<selectable>TOE platform</selectable></selectables>
					shall provide alternate functionality to standard X.509 certificate revocation checking 
					for the following exceptions: 
					<selectables linebreak="yes">
						<selectable>firmware checking of updates: 
							invalidate automatic updates if the firmware certificate is compromised</selectable>
						<selectable><assignable>other exceptions and corresponding functionality</assignable></selectable></selectables>.
					</title>
				<aactivity>
					<TSS>
						<h:p>
							The evaluator shall ensure the TSS describes, for each exception, the alternate functionality the TOE implements to 
							handle the lack of certificate revocation. The description must be consistent with the selection in the requirement.
						</h:p>
					</TSS>
					<Guidance>
						<h:p>
							If revocation exceptions are configurable, 
							the evaluator shall ensure the guidance documentation includes the exceptions that can be configured 
							and the steps for doing this.
						</h:p>
					</Guidance>
					<Tests>
						<h:p>
							For each exception, the evaluator shall configure the TSF as necessary to meet the exceptional condition described and exercise the 
							function using a certificate chain without revocation information. 
							The evaluator shall attempt to examine TSF logs or behavior as described in the TSS to confirm the alternative action 
							described is performed. For example, in the case of firmware updates that invalidate automatic updates, 
							the evaluator shall invoke an automatic update and observe that the update is not performed. 
							In other cases, the TSS describes the alternative action.
						</h:p>
					</Tests>
				</aactivity>
			</f-element>
			<audit-event/>
		</f-component>
	</sec:fia>

</sec:Security_Functional_Requirements>
  
<!--                    -->
<!-- Appendix A: Optional Requirements 	-->
<!--                    -->
	
<appendix id="appendix-optional-plus" title="Optional Requirements">  

    <!-- Contents of the appendix are totally generated by "optional-appendix-plus" xsl template. 
         Includes boilerplate, headers, audit table. So the below is not needed. But there is is. -->
    <!--    <audit-table table="optional">
	  Auditable events for Optional SFRs:<h:br/><h:br/>
	</audit-table>  -->
</appendix> 

<!--                    -->
<!-- Appendix B: Selection-based Requirements 	-->
<!--                    -->

    <appendix id="appendix-sel-based" title="Selection-Based Requirements"> 
       
    <!-- Contents of the appendix are totally generated by "optional-appendix" xsl template. 
         Includes boilerplate, headers, audit table. So the below is not needed. But there is is. -->
    <!--    <audit-table table="sel-based">
	  Auditable events for Selecton-based Requirements:	
	</audit-table>   -->
    </appendix> 
	
<!--                    -->
<!-- Appendix C: References 	-->
<!--                    -->
	
   <bibliography>
		<entry id="bibCEM">
   		<tag>CEM</tag>
   		<description>
   			<h:a href="https://commoncriteriaportal.org/files/ccfiles/CEM2022R1.pdf">Common
   				Methodology for Information Technology Security Evaluation - Evaluation Methodology</h:a>,
   			CCMB-2022-11-006, CEM:2022, Revision 1, November 2022. </description>
   	</entry>
		<entry id="bibRFC2986">
			<tag>RFC 2986</tag>
			<description>
				<h:a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc2986">PKCS #10: Certification Request Syntax Specification
					Version 1.7</h:a>
			</description>
		</entry>   
		<entry id="bibRFC5280 ">
			<tag>RFC 5280 </tag>
			<description>
				<h:a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc5280">Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate
					and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile</h:a>
			</description>
		</entry>   
		<entry id="bibRFC6066">
			<tag>RFC 6066</tag>
			<description>
				<h:a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc6066">Transport Layer Security (TLS) Extensions: Extension
					Definitions</h:a>
			</description>
		</entry>   
		<entry id="bibRFC6960">
			<tag>RFC 6960</tag>
			<description>
				<h:a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc6960">X.509 Internet Public Key Infrastructure Online Certificate
					Status Protocol – OCSP </h:a>
			</description>
		</entry>   
		<entry id="bibRFC6961">
			<tag>RFC 6961</tag>
			<description>
				<h:a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc6961">The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Multiple Certificate Status
					Request Extension</h:a>
			</description>
		</entry>   
		<entry id="bibRFC7030">
			<tag>RFC 7030</tag>
			<description>
				<h:a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc7030">Enrollment over Secure Transport</h:a>
			</description>
		</entry>   
		<entry id="bibRFC8603">
			<tag>RFC 8603</tag>
			<description>
				<h:a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc8603">Commercial National Security Algorithm (CNSA) Suite Certificate
					and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile</h:a>
			</description>
		</entry>
    </bibliography>
</Package>
